Guide to the Stephen Parks Research Collection on Charles Cotton
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Stephen Parks research collection on Charles Cotton
1962-1987
OSB MSS 104
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.33
(2 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, and copies documenting Stephen Parks's research regarding Charles Cotton's autograph and handwriting in order to authenticate a manuscript copy of Cotton's poem, "Contentation." Research files include correspondence, notes, photocopies, and photographs of Cotton manuscripts from repositories including the Beinecke, Bodleian, British, Clark, Derby Borough, Houghton, Huntington, and New York Public Libraries, as well as dealers and scholars including Peter Croft and Alvin Dust. Research copies consist of manuscripts, including a complete copy the Derby Manuscript; photographs of manuscripts used in Parks's article on Cotton; dealer catalogs; and secondary sources.
Parks, Stephen, 1940-
Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Stephen Parks, February 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Charles Cotton (1630-1687) was an English poet and translator. He is best known for writing the second part of Izaak Walton's The Compleat Angler.
Stephen Parks was the Curator of the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection at the Beinecke Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1972 to 2004. Parks authenticated a Charles Cotton manuscript, "Contentation" (Osborn fb64), in his paper, "Charles Cotton and the Derby Manuscript" (in Stephen Parks and P.J. Croft, Literary Autographs, University of California, Los Angeles: William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, 1983).
Scope and Contents
The Stephen Parks Research Collection on Charles Cotton consists of correspondence, notes, and research copies, spanning the years 1962-1987. The collection documents Stephen Parks's research regarding the handwriting of Charles Cotton (1630-1687), in order to authenticate a manuscript copy of Cotton's poem, "Contentation" (Osborn fb65). The collection is housed in 2 boxes (including 1 oversize box) and has been organized into two series: Research Files and Research Copies.
Series I, Research Files, is arranged alphabetically by name of file in folders 1-33. The files relate to the libraries, antiquarian book dealers, and individuals that Parks contacted in the course of his research, as well as some research subjects, and include correspondence, notes, photocopies, and photographs of Charles Cotton manuscripts. Repositories with which Parks corresponded include the Beinecke, Bodleian, British, Clark, Houghton, Huntington, and New York Public Libraries, as well as the Derby Borough Library. Among the individuals with whom Parks corresponded are Peter Croft and Alvin Dust.
Series II, Research Copies, is arranged by type of material in folders 34-43. The research copies consist of photocopies and photographs of Charles Cotton manuscripts, dealer catalogs listing Cotton-related material, Cotton-related secondary sources, and miscellaneous secondary sources. The copies include a complete copy of the Derby Manuscript, the primary manuscript source of Cotton's poetry. It is a commonplace book of verses kept by members of the Fitzherbert family, friends of Cotton's. The original is in the collection of the Derby Borough Library. Copies of Cotton manuscripts also include photographs used by Parks in "Charles Cotton and the Derby Manuscript."
Authors, English -- Autographs; English poetry -- Early modern, 1500-1700 -- Manuscripts; Cotton, Charles, 1630-1687 -- Manuscripts; Croft, P. J. (Peter John), 1929-1984; Parks, Stephen, 1940-
- Research Files, 1962-84; Series I; 33
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Research Files, is arranged alphabetically by folder title. File titles in brackets were supplied during processing.
  - Beinecke Library, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - [Bevan, Jonquil], 1980 Oct 16 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [Bletcher], 1976 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bodleian Library, 1977 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - British Library, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [Chapple, John], 1982 Apr-May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clark Library, 1982 Jan-Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Clarke, Thomas], 1977 Mar 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [Croft, Peter], 1962-82 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Derby Borough Library, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Derbyshire Records Office, 1976-81 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Dust, Allen], 1975-84 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Facsimilies, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Printed reproductions of Cotton's autograph
  - [Goodspeed's Book Shop], 1977 Mar 31 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - [The Grolier Club], 1977 Mar (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - [Hatchwell, Richard], 1975 Nov (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Houghton Library, 1975-82 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - H. P. Kraus Rare Books & Manuscripts, 1978 Apr (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Huntington Library, 1977 Mar (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - [Kirschenbaum], 1980 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - [Library of Congress], 1977 Apr (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - [The Newberry Library], 1977 Apr (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York Public Library, 1977 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Not Traced, 1977-80 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - [Notes], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Osborn Collection, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - [Pool, J. Lawrence], 1977 Dec 21 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [Princeton University Library], 1977 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - [Seven Gables Book Shop], 1977 Mar (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - [Simpson, John], 1978 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - [Staffordshire County Council], 1977 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - [Traylen, Charles W.], 1980 Aug (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - [Walter R. Benjamin Autographs], 1977 Mar (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Research Copies, n.d.; Series II; 10
  Series II, Research Copies, is arranged by type of material.
  - Copies of Cotton manuscripts
    - Copy of the Derby Manuscript (ca. 1660-66), n.d.
    - Photographs of Cotton manuscripts, plates 1-9 from Parks, "Charles Cotton and the Derby Manuscript" (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Oversize copies of plate 8 from Parks, "Charles Cotton and the Derby Manuscript"
    - Photocopies of Charles Cotton manuscripts, printed autographs, and typescripts (ca. 1660s, 1836) (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Copies of dealer catalogs listing Charles Cotton-related material (1848-1985), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Copies of Charles Cotton-related secondary sources (1759-1987) (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Copies of miscellaneous secondary sources (1848-1961) (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Oversize, 5; (1 box)
  - Copy of the Derby Manuscript (ca. 1660-66) (in Series II), n.d. (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 39-42)
  - Oversize copies of plate 8 from Parks, "Charles Cotton and the Derby Manuscript" (in Series II) (Box 2 (Oversize), Folder 43)